<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="ReleaseNotesR2026a"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>GMAT R2026a Release Notes</title>

  <para>The General Mission Analysis Tool (GMAT) version R2026a was released
  in April 2026 and is the 16th release for the project. The previous public
  release was in April 2025. This is a major project release that includes
  numerous improvements and enhancements in general capabilities and models, 
  mission design and orbit determination functionality, visualization, and 
  improved cross-platform compatibility.</para>
  <para>Below, we give a summary of key changes in this release.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Milestones and Accomplishments</title>

    <para>We are excited that GMAT continues to see significant adoption for
    operational mission support.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT is being used as the primary operational tool for maneuver
        planning by the Space weather Observations at L1 to Advance 
		Readiness – 1 (SOLAR-1) flight dynamics team.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT is being used as the primary operational tool for maneuver
        planning by the Roman Space Telescope (RST) flight dynamics
        team.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT orbit determination is the primary tool used by the NASA
        GSFC Flight Dynamics Facility (FDF) to support various missions in
        LEO, GEO, Lunar, Lagrange point, and other orbit regimes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>For the first time in GMAT release history, the <link
    xlink:href="https://github.com/nasa/GMAT"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/nasa/GMAT</link>
    GitHub repo will soon be used to disseminate select code updates to prior
    to the next public release.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Major Improvements and Enhancements</title>

    <section>
      <title>General Capabilities and Models</title>

      <para>The following general capabilities are new to R2026a:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable exponential atmospheres at all solar system bodies
          (GMT-8449, GMT-8160). GMAT’s drag modeling can now model atmospheres
          at any solar system body, using an exponential model based on the
          exponential drag model found in Fundamentals of Astrodynamics and
          Applications by David Vallado. Users need to supply a file
          containing the coefficients for the model. Examples of this file for
          the Earth and Mars can be found in the data/atmosphere folders in
          the release. See the <filename>Ex_ForceModels.script</filename> in 
		  the application samples directory for an example of this capability.
		  </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Upgrade the ground track component to be extendable and work
          on macOS (GMT-8451, GMT-8507). The GMAT GroundTrackPlot component
          has been replaced by a custom GroundTrack component. The new
          component is scripted identically to the older component and is
          identified by the object name GroundTrack in script. Scripts that
          use GroundTrackPlot as the object type being created now create the
          replacement component rather than the older type. GroundTrack
          objects fill their windows completely, rather than preserving a 2:1
          aspect ratio.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add the MSISE-00 Atmospheric Model to the public release
          (GMT-8487). GMAT now includes the 2001 United States Naval Research
          Laboratory Mass Spectrometer and Incoherent Scatter Radar Exosphere
          (NRLMSISE00) atmospheric model for use in drag modeling. See the
          <filename>Ex_ForceModels</filename> script in the application 
		  samples directory for an example of this capability.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Replace OrbitView with OpenFramesInterface (OFI) by mapping
          the OV scripting to an OFI window (GMT-8322). GMAT, using a new
          default libOVtoOFI plugin, automatically maps OrbitView 3d
          visualization objects to an OpenFramesInterface window. OrbitView is
          deprecated and subject to removal in a future release, but users can
          for now disable the libOVtoOFI plugin in the startup file if they
          want to use the deprecated OrbitView.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Update SPICE inputs readers and writers to treat MJ2000Eq and
          ICRF coordinate systems correctly (GMT-5211, GMT-8468, GMT-8300).
          GMAT will now properly interpret SPICE planetary ephemeris files and
          other SPICE ephemeris files as ICRF. GMAT will also transform states
          to ICRF when writing SPICE files. As a result of this, users may
          notice slight differences in the results of computations, including
          propagation using multiple point-masses, orbit determination, and
          coordinate transformations involving translations to other
          bodies.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fix Lagrange Interpolator for intermediate points and
          ascending/descending data (GMT-8443). Updated the embedded Lagrange
          interpolator to properly interpolate data where the independent
          variable (e.g., time for an ephem or mass for a center of mass file)
          is either ascending or descending.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Error and exit when a user specifies a non-existing startup
          file (GMT-7802). GMAT issues an error and exits when using
          –startup_file command line argument if the specified startup file
          does not exist.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Enable third bodies for SRP shadow calculations (GMT-6543,
          GMT-8403). A new ForceModel parameter, SRP.ExtraShadowBodies is now
          available. This can be used to model SRP shadow effects due to
          bodies in addition to the force model central body, which is always
          considered for shadow modeling. See the
          <filename>Ex_ForceModel_ExtraShadowBodies</filename> script in the 
		  application samples directory.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Refactor the ShadowState code (GMT-8077). The GMAT code
          associated with performing percent shadow calculations was
          refactored to be more maintainable.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Increase the parameters a user can "Get" in the
          MissionSequence (GMT-8111, GMT-8363). Even though GMAT has the
          ability for users to configure resource object (e.g. Spacecraft,
          Propagator, DC, Optimizers, Impulsive or FiniteBurns) parameters
          before the mission sequence starts, a user cannot get all of those
          object parameters in the mission sequence. This work expands the
          parameters a user can retrieve during the mission sequence run.
          GMT-8111 and GMT-8363 details the impacted parameters.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Generalizing the use of the Intrusion Locator (GMT-7572,
          GMT-8332, GMT-8482). The intrusion locator introduced in GMAT R2022a
          has been enhanced to allow sensor intrusion calculations for bodies
          that are not the central body of the model. This capability enables
          the calculation of transits and occultations as seen by a
          spacecraft. See the 
		  <filename>Ex_IntrusionLocator_Mercury_Sun_Transit</filename> script
          in the application samples directory.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fix ground station mask file issue with conflicting NAIF Ids
          (GMT-8416). Internal NAIF ID generation for FOV frames used by
          ground stations in a ContactLocator have been updated to ensure
          unique values when numerous ground stations are used. This prevents
          one FOV being overwritten by another within SPICE from matching
          IDs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add logic for ephemeris generation when steps in the segment
          are less than the interpolation order (GMT-8238). The ephemeris
          propagation code in GMAT now reduces that the order of the state
          interpolator to match the number of points available in each
          ephemeris segment, so that interpolated states can be generated for
          segments that do not have enough points for the scripted
          interpolation. When the interpolation uses fewer points than needed
          for the scripted interpolation, GMAT posts a message in the message
          window identifying the segment and the interpolation order used in
          that segment.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Update CSALT interface scripts and add tutorials (GMT-8298).
          Additional guidance have been added to show users how to create a
          CSALT project in Visual Studio, describe the main CSALT C++ base
          classes that must be inherited to use the tool, and six example
          tutorials. Each tutorial sequentially adds additional CSALT features
          available to create and solve optimal control problems.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add built-In quaternion functions (GMT-8110, GMT-8371). Three
          new quaternion functions are now available in GMAT:
          QuaternionRotation, QuaternionProduct, and QuaternionToDCM. The use
          of these functions can be found in the Users Guide.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Enhance ability to use SPICE for coordinate system
          transformations (GMT-8255, GMT-8300). Reference frames defined in
          the SPICE toolkit may now be used in GMAT by creating a coordinate
          system using the SPICE Axes type. Useful examples of this are Moon
          Principal Axes (PA) and Mean Earth (ME) frames, but the IAU frames
          for other bodies can also be defined and employed through assignment
          of the appropriate kernels. See the <filename>Ex_SPICECoordinateAxes
		  </filename> script in the application samples directory.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Update help system by replacing the .chm file with .html
          (Tutorial/User Guide) (GMT-8500). Previous versions of GMAT utilized
          Compiled HTML Help (CHM) files but this file format is obsolete and
          not supported, so GMAT releases moving forward will point to the
          HTML files provided.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section>
        <title>Beta- and Alpha-level Capabilities</title>

        <para>These are new features that have not yet undergone full testing
        and may have bugs. To access some of these features, you may need to
        edit the <filename>bin/gmat_startup_file.txt</filename> file to load
        the desired alpha plug-in and/or activate features only available in
        testing mode (set RUN_MODE = TESTING in the file). These features
        should be used with caution.</para>

        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Python GMD writer for UTDF one-way downlink range-rate
            tracking (GMT-8228, GMT-8229). The python utility located in
            "\utilities\python\navigation\utdf_to_gmd.py" has been updated to
            add support for one-way downlink range-rate tracking. This utility
            reads a raw UTDF tracking data and converts it to the GMD format
            that GMAT can ingest.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Navigation and Orbit Determination (OD)</title>

      <para>The following navigation and orbit determination capabilities are
      new to R2026a:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>New operational data types for orbit determination
          (navigation)</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>GN/DTE one-way downlink range-rate tracking (GMT-8226,
              GMT-8227). GMAT now supports one-way downlink range-rate
              measurements in km/sec for orbit determination. This extends the
              existing RangeRate data type to one-way downlink RangeRate in
              addition to the existing two-way, and three-way RangeRate
              measurements. See the <filename>Ex_Estimate_RangeRangeRate
			  </filename> script in the application samples/Navigation 
			  directory.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Batch estimator report hostname value unrecognizable
          (GMT-8275). Under certain circumstances the GMAT hostname was not
          properly displayed in the estimator report file. Text associated
          with the computer hostname is now properly printed out in the
          estimator report file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Improve navigation ionosphere modeling performance (GMT-8459,
          GMT-8168). Refactor of the previous FORTRAN to C (f2c) ionosphere
          code to improve the speed of the ionosphere correction computation
          when in use.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The following navigation and orbit determination capabilities have
      changed in R2026a:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Corrected a bug in the inner-loop data editing scheme
          (GMT-7281). A bug affecting the batch estimator inner-loop editing
          scheme has been corrected. The BatchEstimator inner-loop now
          functions properly. Users may find the inner-loop editor helps
          shorten estimation run time by reducing the number of iterations
          required to converge.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The following navigation and orbit determination capabilities are
      deprecated beginning with R2026a:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>None.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Scripting and API Interface</title>

      <para>The following Scripting and API Interface changes were implemented
      in R2026a:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>The following parameters have been prevented from being set in
          the MissionSequence:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>NAIFIdReferenceFrame, SPADSRPInterpolationMethod,
              SPADDragInterpolationMethod, ModelFile, ModelOffsetX,
              ModelOffsetY, ModelOffsetZ, ModelRotationX, ModelRotationY,
              ModelRotationZ, ModelScale, NAIFId, Id</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Optimal Control</title>

      <section>
        <title>Beta Capabilities</title>

        <para>The GMAT Optimal Control capability remains a Beta feature for
        R2026a.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>OpenFramesInterface Visualizations</title>

      <note>
        <para>The OFI continues to be the primary 3D visualization component
        in GMAT. <guilabel>OrbitView</guilabel> is deprecated and will no
        longer be supported. Users are encouraged to migrate their scripts
        from <guilabel>OrbitView</guilabel> to
        <guilabel>OpenFramesInterface</guilabel>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>The complete set of documentation for OFI is available at <link
      xlink:href="https://gitlab.com/EmergentSpaceTechnologies/OpenFramesInterface/-/wikis/home"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">the OFI Wiki</link></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Other Improvements</title>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Corrected issue GMT-8427, OpenFramesInterface New Vector view
        panel does not resize properly.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Corrected issue GMT-8355, OpenFramesView panel does not display
        correctly.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Enable OpenFramesInterface font options (GMT-8536).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Corrected issue GMT-6571, SystemTime() fails on rerun when first
        run was interrupted.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Compatibility Changes</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enabled support for Mac Intel Machines (GMT-8340). On macOS,
        GMAT is now distributed as a universal application. Future versions of
        the GMAT Mac application may not fully support the Intel chipset due
        to third party dependency limitations (e.g., MATLAB interface).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Fixed notarization of the Mac application (GMT-8339).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI items don't scale on high DPI displays due to WxWidgets
        limitation (workaround) (GMT-6125).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Update SWIG to the current release (GMT-8299).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Update the build system to use CMake 4 (GMT-8434).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Resolve missing OSG plugins (GMT-8242/GMT-8523).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Remove or reconfigure PCRE in the dependency configuration
        (GMT-8530).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Support for Python 3.6 through 3.8 has been discontinued.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Fixed &amp; Known Issues</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Issues</title>

      <para>29 high priority bugs were closed in this release. See the "<link
      xlink:href="https://gmat.atlassian.net/issues/?filter=15286"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Critical Issues Fixed in
      R2026a</link>" report for details. Some significant fixes in R2026a
      include:</para>

      <informaltable frame="topbot">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="0.2*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">ID</entry>

              <entry align="left">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry align="left"><link
              xlink:href="https://gmat.atlassian.net/browse/GMT-8357"
              xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GMT-8357</link></entry>

              <entry align="left">GMAT on Linux crashes and report generation
              fails for external force model script.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="left"><link
              xlink:href="https://gmat.atlassian.net/browse/GMT-8160"
              xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GMT-8160</link></entry>

              <entry align="left">Mars exponential atmosphere has no effect.</entry>
            </row>

          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Known Issues</title>

      <para>See the "<link
      xlink:href="https://gmat.atlassian.net/issues/?filter=15285"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">All Known Critical Issues for
      R2026a</link>" report for a list of all known major issues in R2026a.
      There are several known issues in this release that we consider to be
      significant:</para>

      <para><informaltable frame="topbot">
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="0.2*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">ID</entry>

                <entry align="left">Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry align="left"><link
                xlink:href="https://gmat.atlassian.net/browse/GMT-8024"
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GMT-8024</link></entry>

                <entry align="left">Windows Defender pop-up may appear
                preventing users from initially opening the GMAT application
                and require additional user actions.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
